L’Aerophile Collection
Science, Technology, & Business Division, Library of Congress
- Corporations, 1920s-1940s (Boxes 23-44)
  - Lincoln Arc Welding, Lockheed, Loire Nieuport, Lorenz, Luscombe, Martin, Material Telephonique, Maubousin, Moulet & Cie. (Box 30)
    - Luscombe Airplane Development Corporation. (Envelope 7)
      - Simple airplane schematics. (Item 4)
    - Martin, Moulet & Cie. (Envelope 8)
      - Two Photographs of a Laboratory. (Item 1)
      - Two Photographs of pumps. (Item 2)
      - A technical report on Self-regulating pumps. (Item 3)
      - Publication: “Appareils AM” # 701 and supplement. (Item 4)
    - Le Material Telephonique. (Envelope 9)
      - Publication “Automatic Radiocompas Type RC.5 for Airplanes.” (Item 1)
    - Avions Mauboussin. (Envelope 10)
      - Blue-print and specification sheet for M-300 and M-302 airplanes. (Item 1)
      - Publication: Mauboussin Avions #11. (Item 2)
      - Characteristics and specifications of the Mauboussin M-300. (Item 3)
      - Characteristics and specifications of the Mauboussin M-400. (Item 4)
      - Page 4 of publication: Planeur (glider) “Castel-Mauboussin.” (Item 5)
      - Page 6 of publication: Planeur (glider) “Castel-Mauboussin” “Ailette.” (Item 6)
      - Drawings of a Mauboussin type 123. (Item 7)
      - Drawings of a Mauboussin type FM. 160. (Item 8)
      - Drawings of a Mauboussin Zodiac XII. (Item 9)
      - “Information on the International Challenge” Two pages. (Item 10)
      - Two blue-prints of the Mauboussin type XII. (Item 11)
      - Publication: Planes for Tourism Mauboussin. (Item 12)
      - “Planes for tourism and training” series 1939 for the Mauboussin type I27 and 200. (Item 13)
      - Specifications for the Mauboussin type M. I90. (Item 14)
      - “Planes for tourism, school or training” series 1938. Mauboussin 123, 125. (Item 15)
      - Specifications for the Mauboussin type M. I60. (Item 16)
      - Drawing of the Mauboussin 123. (Item 17)
      - Specifications, blue-prints, photographs and a letter sent to L’Aerophile. (Item 18)
      - Publication: “Presentation and maintenance of Maubousin Aircraft.” (Item 19)
      - “Mauboussin Airplanes” includes characteristics, specifications and drawings for some aircraft. (Item 20)
      - Questionnaire filled out by Mauboussin, sent to L’Aerophile. (Item 21)
      - Specifications for Mauboussin type 200. (Item 22)
      - Unidentified airplane photograph. (Item 23)
  - Max Holste, Messier, Mojneau, Morane-Saulnier, Mureaux, Nardi, Noordnyn, Normalair, North American, Northrop. (Box 31)
    - Max Holste. (Envelope 1)
    - Messier (Etablissements). (Envelope 2)
    - R. Moineau. (Envelope 3)
    - Morane- Saulnier. (Envelope 4)
    - Mureaux. (Envelope 5)
    - Nardi. (Envelope 6)
    - Noorduyn Aircraft Ltd. (Envelope 7)
    - Normalair. (Envelope 8)
    - North American Aviation Inc. (Envelope 9)
    - North American Aviation Inc. (Envelope 10)
    - North American Aviation Inc. (Envelope 11)
    - North American Aviation Inc. (Envelope 12)
    - Northrop Aircraft Inc. (Envelope 13)
  - Paul Aubert, Phillips & Pain, Phillips & Powis, Piper, Platt – LePage, Porterfield, Potez, Potterat Metalworking, Rear Vin, Rellumit. (Box 32)
    - Paul Aubert (Avions). (Envelope 1)
    - Philips & Pain (Etablissements). (Envelope 2)
    - Phillips & Powis Aircraft Ltd. (Envelope 3)
    - Piper Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 4)
    - Porterfield Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 5)
    - Potez Avions #1 (SNCA). (Envelope 6)
    - Potez Avions #2. (Envelope 7)
    - Potterat, Metal Working Machines. (Envelope 8)
    - Rear Win Aircraft & Engines Inc. (Envelope 9)
    - Rellumit. (Envelope 10)
  - Renard, Richard, Ryan, Seversky, Short Brothers, Siebee, Sikorsky, SNCA. (Box 33)
    - Renard. (Envelope 1)
    - J. Richard. (Envelope 2)
    - Rose Airplane Corporation. (Envelope 3)
    - Rotol Ltd. (Envelope 4)
    - Ryan Aeronautical Company. (Envelope 5)
    - Ryan Aeronautical Company. (Envelope 6)
    - Seversky Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 7)
    - Short Brothers. (Envelope 8)
    - Siebel Flugzeugwerke. (Envelope 9)
    - Sikorsky Aircraft. (Envelope 10)
    - S.N.C.A. S.O. (Envelope 11)
    - S.N.C.A. du Sud Est. (Envelope 12)
  - SNCA (Hanriot), Soc. Aerienne Bordolaise, Son. Anon. Belge, Soc. Constr d'Aviation Legere, Soc. d'Etudes Aeronautiques, Soc. Fran. d'Aviation Nouvelle, Soc. Franc. de Construct. Aeron., Soc. Gen. du Magnesium. (Box 34)
    - Hanriot #1 (S.N.C.A.). (Envelope 1)
    - Hanriot #2 (S.N.C.A.). (Envelope 2)
    - SNCASO. (Envelope 3)
    - Societe Aerienne Bordelaise. (Envelope 4)
    - Societe Anonyme Belge de Constructions Aeronautiques. (Envelope 5)
    - Societe Constructions d’Aviation Legere. (Envelope 6)
    - Societe d’Etudes Aeronautiques. (Envelope 7)
    - Societe Francaise d’Aviation Nouvelle. (Envelope 8)
    - Societe De Constructions Aeronautiques. (Envelope 9)
    - Societe Generale du Magnesium. (Envelope 10)
  - Soc. Mecanique generale, Soc. Nat. de Constr. Aeron. du Centre, Soc. Provencale de Constr. Aero., Spartan, Stinson, Taylor, Tecalemit, Timm. Tipsy. (Box 35)
    - Societe du Mercanique Generale. (Envelope 1)
    - Societe Nationale de Constructions Aeronautique du Centre. (Envelope 2)
    - Societe Provencale de Constructions Aeronautique. (Envelope 3)
    - Spartan Aircraft Company. (Envelope 4)
    - Taylor Aircraft Company (“The Club”). (Envelope 5)
    - Tecalemit. (Envelope 6)
    - Timm Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 7)
    - Tipsy Aircraft Co. Ltd. (Envelope 8)
  - TWA, United, VIA, Vickers, Vultee, Waco, Walter, Weick, Weir, Westland, Williamson Photographic. (Box 36)
    - TWA. (Envelope 1)
    - United Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 2)
    - VIA. (Envelope 3)
    - Vickers Ltd. (Envelope 4)
    - Vultee Aircraft. (Envelope 5)
    - Waco Aircraft Corporation. (Envelope 6)
    - Walter. (Envelope 7)
    - G.&J. Weir, Ltd. (Envelope 8)
    - Fred E. Weick & Associates. (Envelope 9)
    - Westland Aircraft Ltd. (Envelope 10)
    - Williamson (Photographic Engineers). (Envelope 11)
  - Books (Box 37)
    - Album: drawings of Montgolfiere-type balloons which ascended from Tarragona (Spain) in 1876. (Item 1)
    - Variable Pitch propellers Log Book, London: HMSO. 1949. (Item 2)
    - Instructions on Setting up, Adjusting, and Care of Clerget Rotary Engine, Washington, GPO. 1920. (Item 3)
    - L'Ecole' d'Ader. (Item 4)
    - DERULUFT – "German-Russian Aeronautical Company." (Item 5)
    - Le Spactateur Militaire. Paris. 1887. (Item 6)
  - Books (Box 38)
    - Les Usines - publications of Hispano-Suiza Corp. (Item 1)
    - L'Aviation Francaise. Special ed. of L'Illustration Economique et Financiere. 20 Mai 1922. (Item 2)
    - Two Aerial Voyages of Dr. Jefferies & Mons. Blanchard. London. Reprinted 1786., (2 copies). (Item 3)
    - Rallye du Hoggar. 1936. (Item 4)
    - George H. Dowty: Retractable Undercarriages. 1935. (Item 5)
    - 4th Internationales Flugmeeting, Zurich 1937 and other programs. (Item 6)
    - Medal: Concours des Jeunes Tigres Cree par l’Aérophile Section de Grenoble. (Item 7)
    - Medal: “In Eo PatriÆ Spes,” A. Borrell, 1894. (Item 8)
    - Medal: “Feriam Sedera,” M. Dammann, 1920. (Item 9)
  - Photo Album: Congresses Int. de Fiat; Germans marching into Paris 1940; liberation of Paris, 1944. (Box 39)
    - Group photograph of the Congress at Brussels, 1911. (Item 1)
    - Group photograph of the Congress in Rome, 1922. (Item 2)
    - Group photograph of the Congress in Gothenburg, Sweden, 1923. (Item 3)
    - Group photograph signed by the members of the Copenhagen Congress in 1929, held at the Chateau de Christiansborg. (Item 4)
    - Group photograph from the Copenhagen Congress, 1929. (Item 5)
    - Group photograph from a 1924 Congress. (Item 6)
    - Group photograph from the 1929 Paris Congress. (Item 7)
    - Two group photographs from a 1924 meeting in Paris. (Item 8)
    - Group photograph “Comite” Bern, December, 1939. (Item 9)
    - Seven photographs of German troops arriving in Paris, June 14, 1940. (Item 10)
    - Four photographs of German military vehicles leaving Paris, August 20, 1944. (Item 11)
    - Two photographs “Represailles” (Reprisals) in Paris, August 21, 1944. (Item 12)
    - Five photographs “Liberation” in Paris, August 21 and 25, 1944. (Item 13)
    - Twelve photographs from August 26, 1944. The photographs include scenes of General de Gaulle’s speech and parade down the Champs-Élysées. (Item 14)
    - Four group photographs from the Fédération Aéronautique Internationale (FAI) Conference in Cleveland, Ohio, 1949. (Item 15)
    - Two group photographs from the FAI Conference in Stockholm, 1950. (Item 16)
    - Group photograph from the FAI Conference in Spain, 1952. (Item 17)
  - Flying events. (Box 40)
    - Conference Notes, 1924 Aero Club. (Envelope 1)
      - Notes by Monsieur Louis Breguet on 8 November 1924 at Brussels in the presence of the King of Belgium at a reception organized by the Belgian Aero-Club to honor the Captain Pelletier Doisy Warrant Besin. (Item 1)
    - Aerodromes de la Region Parisienne. (Envelope 2)
      - Two maps of Aérodromes in the Paris region drawn to scale. (Item 1)
    - Advertisements for Aircrafts. (Envelope 3)
      - Pamphlet describing Wright Brothers’ accomplishments. (Item 1)
      - French brochure encouraging people to consider aircraft travel rather than vehicle travel. Title reads, “The road is crowded; the sky is free ...” (Item 2)
      - Program for the 11th annual French Aero-Club’s Grand Prix for Balloons, 1922. (Item 3)
    - Advertisements for Air Shows. (Envelope 4)
      - Poster for French Balloon show. (Item 1)
      - Postcard for 1909 French Air Show. (Item 2)
    - Advertisements for Air Shows (Italy). (Envelope 5)
      - Poster advertising Italian air show sponsored by the Naples’ Aero Club. (Item 1)
    - Advertisements for Air Shows (Spain). (Envelope 6)
      - Two posters for Ibero-American air show (1929), sponsored by the Real Aero Club of Andalusia. (Item 1)
    - Air Transport (Clipping). (Envelope 7)
      - Photograph of cargo of pineapples. (Item 1)
    - R. Alkan & Cie. (Envelope 8)
      - Blueprints for engine parts. (Item 1)
      - One unidentified mounted photograph. (Item 2)
    - Anniversary notices for balloonists Charles, Montgolfieres, Duro. (Envelope 9)
      - Small brochure shaped and colored like a balloon for the 1951 Festival celebrating Paris’ bi-millennium and the story of the Montgolfiers. (Item 1)
      - Invitation to centenary celebration of physicist Jaques Alexander Charles sponsored by the Aero-Club of France, 1923. (Item 2)
      - Invitation to a dinner to honor the anniversary of the traverse of Jesus-Pernandez Duro, 1907. (Item 3)
    - Aviation Events 1948 #1. (Envelope 10)
      - Photo release for XB-45 which could reach speeds of over 480 miles/hour. More than 100 were being built for the Air Force at the time. (Item 1)
      - Two photographs of special aides at the technical conference of IATA (International Air Transport Association), 1948. (Item 2)
      - Two photographs of R.E. Bishop, Chief designer of the de Havilland Aircraft Company (right), Major Sir Miles Thomas, Deputy Chairman of the British Overseas Airway Cooperation (center), Frank B. Halford, Chairman and Technical director of the Havilland Engine Company (left, discussing the progress of the de Havilland D.H. 106 jet airliner project. (Item 3)
      - Photograph of W/Cdr. A.N. (Bill) Kingwill, veteran aeronautical training expert, who had at the time, over 30 years of flying experience. He demonstrated the Prentice in the Argentine and was planning to test fly the first machine to be handed over at Cordoba. (Item 4)
      - Photograph of prentices destined for the Argentine Air Force on the production line in Percival’s Luton factory. (Item 5)
      - Photograph of a Percival Prentice three seat Basic Trainer wearing the Argentine colors awaits shipment to South America where it will form part of the equipment of the Argentine Air Force Flying Training Schools, introducing to that country the most modern methods of flying instruction. (Item 6)
      - Photograph of an Argentinean man buying The Percival Prentice: the first Prentice packed for shipment to Argentina. (Item 7)
      - Press release from Huntington Aviation Group noting a British Trainer adopted by the Argentine Air Force. (Item 8)
      - Two photographs of a First Convair-Liner with the markings of a foreign airline in flight. (Item 9)
      - Photograph of the world’s then-smallest and largest flying planes, the 360-pound Wee Bee and Consolidated Vultee’s giant XC-99 military troop transport and cargo plane, respectively. (Item 10)
      - Photograph of “Bristol” Theseus, which successfully completely the 500-hour endurance test. Shown is a front 3/4 view of the Theseus, which was the first gas turbine of its type to be successfully type tested. (Item 11)
      - Photograph of the “Bristol” Theseus, which was installed in the Avro Lincoln. As part of the flight development program Lincoln aircraft at the time had flown many hours with Theseus turbines in the outboard positions. (Item 12)
      - A photograph of the Theseus taken during one of the stop periods that punctuated the test. (Item 13)
      - Another view of the Theseus during a stop period. (Item 14)
      - Photograph of Mr. John Freeman pulling the lever that brought the Theseus turbine to a stop at the end of its 500-hour endurance test. (Item 15)
      - Photograph of Freeman and two other men with the Theseus turbine. (Item 16)
      - Photograph of the Curtiss XP-87, the US Air Force’s newest long range fighter airplane and the first ever powered by four jet engines, takes off. (Item 17)
      - Photograph of John Corby, who was appointed on May 12, 1948 de Havilland Area Manager for the Far East. (Item 18)
      - Photograph of the ruggedly constructed Ryan Navion in flight, used for personal flying in high-altitude countries like Switzerland. (Item 19)
      - Photograph of the four-place Navion, a spacious, conveniently loaded personal-business plane, which packs a load of 1020 pounds. (Item 20)
      - Photograph of a tan 1948 model Ryan Navion, flown by Mademoiselle Jean Guinand of Geneva, Switzerland. The plane had the ability to fly in and out of small fields with ease and had a high, sturdy tricycle landing gear with large, steerable nose-wheel, an important asset in a region where operations were frequently made from rough, unprepared landing strips. (Item 21)
      - Photograph of Navion fliers in India. Mr. Sing is shown; he was an aerodrome officer at Wellington Airport and a member of the Delhi Flying Club. The pictured aircraft was to be a practical tool for business, industrial and government purposes. (Item 22)
      - Photograph of the 3-place Piper Cub Super Cruiser, at the time, the most inexpensive personal airplane in its class. (Item 23)
      - Release from Henry J. Kaufmann & Associates announcing the prize awarded to Rev. Norman E. Kuck, a then-36-year old pastor from Boyne City, Mich. The Reverend received a brand new 1948 Ercoupe for winning first prize in a Mutual network quiz show jungle contest. (Item 24)
      - Bundle of papers and photographs issued by The Press Office of the Bristol Aeroplane Company LTD. England giving the complete description and technical data of the New Type 170 Military Version. Items 26-46 are from the bundle. (Item 25)
      - Booklet detailing the complete performance and operating date in graph form for the New Type 170. (Item 26)
      - Photograph of the New Type 170 in flight. (Item 27)
      - Two photographs of the Military version of the “Bristol” New Type 170 aircraft. (Item 28)
      - Photograph of the control cabin of the dual-controlled New Type 170. (Item 29)
      - Photograph of the equipment hold of the Military New Type 170. (Item 30)
      - Photograph of a Ordnance QF 17-pounder being loaded into the hold of the Military Type 170 Aircraft. (Item 31)
      - Photograph of Nose-opening doors of the New Type 170 Military Transport. (Item 32)
      - Photograph of a 40 M.M. A.A. Bofors Gun being winched into the equipment hold of the military version of the “Bristol” New Type 170 Aircraft. (Item 33)
      - Photograph of a 60-CWT truck emerging form the hold of the New Type 170 Military Aircraft. (Item 34)
      - Photograph of supply dropping with the Military version of the “Bristol” New Type 170. (Item 35)
      - Collection of four photographs supporting the claim that the New Type 170 can easily be adapted to accommodate the very latest survey and photographic reconnaissance equipment. (Item 36)
      - Photograph of the “Bristol” Hercules 672 Engine, a 14 cylinder, two-row, sleeve-valve, air-cooled engine. (Item 37)
      - Photograph of an advanced airfield. (Item 38)
      - Packet of information describing the “Bristol” New Type 170 Military Transport Version. (Item 39)
      - Series of blueprints showing the New Type 170 fitted as an ambulance, troop transport, paratroop transport, proposed typical loads. (Item 40)
      - Diagram of General arrangement freighter – Military version. (Item 41)
      - Diagram of “Freighter” Fuselage Type 170. (Item 42)
      - Diagram of Bristol Type No. 170 – Military Freighter. (Item 43)
      - Photograph of the Hercules 672 “Free-Exit” cowl Engine Installation. (Item 44)
      - Series of three photographs showing (clockwise from top left) ample tying-down rings, a Dodge 3⁄4 ton 4 x 4 Truck with winch is positioned at the read of the aircraft, near the port elevator and a 25 pounder gun/Howitzer shackled in position in the cargo hold of The New Type 170. (Item 45)
      - Papers about the “Bristol” New Type 170 Military Transport Version. (Item 46)
      - Four unidentified photographs. (Item 47)
    - Aviation Events 1948 #2. (Envelope 11)
      - Collection of items, numbered 1-5, from brown envelope with the address, “Miss Santi, “L’Aerophile”, 7, Rue Saint Lazare, Paris 9, FRANCE. Return address, “Bristol.” (Item 1)
      - Photograph of three young heifers posing for the camera before getting on the Freighter. (Item 2)
      - Photograph of the first heifer who must climb on board is led towards the loading ramp. (Item 3)
      - Photograph of the first loaded animals eating their food quickly. (Item 4)
      - Press release from the Bristol Aeroplane Company announcing the transportation of English livestock from Blackbushe to Malta. (Item 5)
      - Collection of items numbered 7-8 from a previously sealed envelope from North American Aviation, Inc. to L’Aerophile, Attn. M.S. La Rougery. Opened 7/1/09. (Item 6)
      - Press release form the North American Aviation, Inc. Municipal Airport in Los Angeles, California announcing the addition of a new two-place Air Force trainer to the company’s model catalog. The trainer was to be used for both primary and basic flight instruction and was to be conventional in design except for its tricycle landing gear – the first primary-basic trainer to be designed to use a tricycle landing gear in the United States. (Item 7)
      - Two photo releases for the T-28 Air Force all purpose trainer, which was to be used to prepare pilots for ultra-high speed jet aircraft. An artist’s sketch is shown. (Item 8)
      - Booklet titled “Avro on the Airlift,” an account of a visit to Germany, for the purpose of studying the contribution made by two Avro Aircraft on the Berlin Air Lift. Includes pictures numbered 10-15. (Item 9)
      - Photograph of A.V.M D.C.T. Bennett leaving his Avro Tudor 5 at Gatow (1949). 1,500 gallons of diesel oil are being discharged through the pipe leading out the door. (Item 10)
      - Photograph of two Avro Tudors ls, operated by British South American Airways on the Berlin Airlift since October, are shown proving their weight carrying capabilities and reliability. (Item 11)
      - Tissue paper insert with “AVRO” logo. Paper reads: “A.V. Roe % Co. Limited with Compliments. Greengate, Middleton, Manchester.” (Item 12)
      - Photograph of the manifest sheet which gave the Avro Tudor 1 load of 20.645 lbs. Photograph shows two Avro Tudors carrying a larger load than any other aircraft on the Airlift. (Item 13)
      - Photograph taken at Gatow shows a line of Avro Yorks on the unloading strip. (Item 14)
      - Photograph of Avro York load of beef fillets and butter occupying the full length of the fuselage and weighing nearly 16,500 lbs. (Item 15)
      - Envelope containing a collection of releases. Envelope is from The De Havilland Aircraft Co., LTD address to L’Aerophile in Paris. Items 17-19. (Item 16)
      - Release from The De Havilland Enterprise announcing Release of information by the British Government, Ground-attack version, Higher-powered versions. (Item 17)
      - Release from The De Havilland Enterprise announcing Significant Vampire Developments; New marks show an indication of the high development potentially of an aircraft already unequalled in fighting effectiveness at altitude. The trend of improvements in both airframe and engine. The photograph attached to the last page is of a Vampire aircraft. (Item 18)
      - Blueprint of Vampire MK. 5 with typical war load. (Item 19)
    - Autographs and Business Cards. (Envelope 12)
      - Business card from Mademoiselle S. Deutsch (de La Meurthe), 4. Place des Etats-Unis. (Item 1)
      - Business card from Le Général Cheutin, former commander of Moroccan Air Force. Card was presented as a gift in 1936. (Item 2)
      - Two business cards from Maurice Bellonte, given as a souvenir. (Item 3)
      - Business card from A. Brocard, Deputy of the Seine and commander of the Legion of Honor. (Item 4)
      - Business card from Colonel De Goÿs, Cabinet chief of Secretary of the State of Aeronautics. (Item 5)
      - Business card from Madame Louise Faure-Favier. (Item 6)
    - French Aviation Maps. (Envelope 13)
      - Map of the study voyages of Noguès in the Mediterranean and the Middle East in 1925 and 1926. (Item 1)
      - Bird’s eye view of the swelling park for “La Coupe Gordon-Bennett” in Genève, August 2-6, 1922. (Item 2)
      - Two maps of the Bourget Air Port. Line at the bottom reads, “A dépense égale, l’Aviation la plus forte fait la plus forte Armée.” (Item 3)
      - Map documenting 65,000 kilometers, 420 flight hours without a single engine or landing issue. On opposite side is a series of four photographs documenting the sudden return from Tokyo to Paris in 6.5 days. (Item 4)
      - Map from the Italian Air National League, showing an aircraft route map. (Item 5)
      - Map on wax paper of South American, European, North African and Middle East flight routes. (Item 6)
      - Map of English towns. (Item 7)
      - Map of Puteaux, France and surrounding areas. (Item 8)
    - French Aviation Letters, Announcements and Invitations. (Envelope 14)
      - Note from Lieutenant Captain Flemming, the author of the article and the conductor of Z.R. III in America. He made a voyage of more than 100 hours and was known as the most experienced captain in the world. (Item 1)
      - Invitation from the President and the members of the organization committee of the National Congress of Colonial Aeronautics. (Item 2)
      - Invitation from the “Master” and the little lady wanted to share the joy and happy landing of their son Pierre. (Item 3)
      - Invitation from Madame Jacques Bellonte to the marriage of her son, Monsieur Maurice Bellontte, Officer of the Honorable Legion with Mademoiselle Raymonde Lafon, 1932. (Item 4)
      - Marriage announcement of Sadi-Lecointe, Officer in the Legion of Honor and Madame Sadi-Lecointe, 8 October 1924. (Item 5)
      - Invitation to the inauguration of the House of Wings by Paul Doumer, then the President of the Republic. Guests were invited to arrive by car, train or plane. (Item 6)